A Guide to the Philip Rahm papers, 1858-1868
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Philip Rahm papers, 1858-1868
The Library of Virginia
53137
.225 cubic feet (1 box)
Philip Rahm
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Purchased
Biographical Information
Philip Rahm was born 13 April 1819 in Bavaria to Peter Rahm (1779-1839) and Elizabeth Jager Rahm (1788-1846). His family emigrated and settled in Richmond, Virginia. Rahm owned and operated Eagle Machine (or Iron) Works with Frank Kahl (1825-1896). Rahm invented a circular saw for use in machine works. Rahm married first Martha Elizabeth Walden (1821-1860) 15 July 1841, and they had eight children. He married second Anna S. Foster (1834-1916) 7 February 1861 and they had 1 child. Rahm died 10 January 1862 from lockjaw that resulted from an injury incurred when helping workmen load a wagon. He was buried in Hollywood Cemetery.
Adolphus James Rahm was born 22 April 1842 in Richmond, Virginia, to Philip Rahm (1819-1862) and Martha Elizabeth Walden Rahm (1821-1860). He attended Episcopal College in Alexandria, Virginia, and joined the Richmond Howitzers when the Civil War began. When his father died, Rahm was released from the army to run the iron works in Richmond. He continued in that line of work, until the last ten years of his life when he became the traveling representative for oil companies. He married Louisa Brownlow Alexander (1850-1920) 9 September 1875, and they had one child. Rahm died 23 June 1906 in Wilmington, North Carolina, and was buried in Hollywood Cemetery.
Scope and Content
Papers, 1858-1868, of Philip Rahm (1819-1862) of Richmond, Virginia. Papers include accounts, agreements, promissory notes, and other papers concerning Rahm's business, Eagle Machine Works (also known as Eagle Iron Works). Also includes shares of stock for the Bank of Richmond to Rahm. Papers also include accounts, clippings, correspondence, inventories, receipts, and other papers of A. J. Rahm as executor of Philip Rahm's estate and as guardian of his brothers.
Contents List
- Articles of agreement, 16 November 1858 (Folder 1)
- Accounts, 1869 (Folder 2)
- Papers, February-August 1860 (Folder 3)
- Papers, September-December 1860 (Folder 4)
- Papers, January-February 1861 (Folder 5)
- Papers, March-December 1861 (Folder 6)
- Accounts, Receipts, 1862-1863 (Folder 7)
- Receipts, 1864 (Folder 8)
- Papers, January-June 1865 (Folder 9)
- Papers, August-October 1865 (Folder 10)
- Papers, November-December 1865 (Folder 11)
- Papers, 1866 (Folder 12)
- Papers, 1867 (Folder 13)
- Correspondence, 1868 (Folder 14)
- Papers, undated (Folder 15)